Hello, and welcome back to
another video with it's Dr.
Dan, and what we're going to be
looking at today is temperature.
So, temperature is one of our most
common measurements that we do in
chemistry, in biology, physics, you name
it, um, in almost every profession we
are always surrounded by temperature.
Um, one of the things you
might look at when you, before
you go outside is, is it hot?
Is it cold out?
Do I need a jacket?
Should I wear shorts?
Are you trying to figure out
exactly what it is that to
prepare yourself for the elements?
So when it comes to temperature, we can
measure it in three different scales
depending on usually where you live and
really what you do for a profession.
Um, now when it comes to these,
so thinking of them, so either
talking of if something is really
hot or if it's really cold, How
do we look at it around the world?
Well, being that I am in the U.
S., the most common way we usually look at
temperature is with the Fahrenheit system.
However, the entire world, for
the most part, uses Celsius.
So one of the things I preach to all
my students is that we need to learn
the Celsius system because it is, we
are a global scientific community.
We need to be able to talk about science
in the same language so that way we can
understand what everybody is working on.
And it's a system that generally
works very, very well mathematically
when it comes to deriving
a lot of our calculations.
Now, Celsius is not the
only system that we'll have.
We also have Kelvin, which is our SI
unit for temperature, believe it or not.
Celsius is a SI derived
unit off of Kelvin.
So this is the metric equivalent, so
it's used generally in the metric system.
Now, what do you usually need to know?
Well, just kind of know
the general difference.
Kelvin is known as an
absolute temperature system.
So it works very, very well when
we're trying to describe the physics
behind how different atoms and
particles and molecules behave.
So absolute means that it
can only be a positive value.
There are no negatives.
So if you notice at the very, very bottom,
what is referred to as absolute zero.
So the coldest temperature theoretically
possible is around zero Kelvin.
And scientists have been trying
to get as close to measuring
absolute zero as possible.
Um, last time I checked, I think
they've got down to nano Kelvin or.
Pico Kelvin.
So 10 to the minus 9 Kelvin.
So very, very close to absolute zero.
When that happens in physics,
it's usually when molecules and
atoms, they don't move anymore.
They stop vibrating and actually moving
and doing what they usually do, right?
They, they are no longer getting excited.
So, um, when, what do we exactly have
to think of in terms of temperature
scales as chemists is we we like to
relate things towards water, right?
Water is what It's about life.
So when it comes to the freezing point
and the boiling point of water, I would
highly recommend, you know, them or
any career path you have, because it
is common knowledge, especially when
it comes to Celsius and Fahrenheit, uh,
Celsius, the boiling point is zero, or
sorry, the freezing point is zero degrees
and the boiling point is 100 degrees C.
So there's a difference of a hundred.
It's very easy to remember.
versus Fahrenheit, uh, 32 degrees
Fahrenheit for freezing and 212
degrees Fahrenheit for boiling.
We also have our common body temperature,
which is around 37 degrees C and room
temperature is around 25 degrees C.
What is temperature all about?
So the definition, just
to put it out there.
So you have it.
is that it's the measure of how
hot or cold something is, right?
So if you go outside, you can
tell how cold or hot it is.
Now, what exactly does this mean?
Well, it's an, it reflects the average
kinetic energy of atoms and molecules.
I mentioned that it had to do with how
much they're vibrating and moving around.
Molecules are moving, even the
solids in your laptop and things
that are just sitting around you
right now, they are vibrating.
So they're moving back and forth.
They're oscillating the atoms.
It might be really slow or you
might not really notice it, right?
Unless you have an
atomic microscope, right?
Which we can't see that far down
with normal conventions is that
they are vibrating all the time.
So when things get excited by
heat, they start moving more and
more and more and they go a little
bit faster and faster and faster.
Versus when they're
cold, they move slower.
Things don't go as fast.
So now keep in mind, temperature
and heat are not the same thing.
Temperature is all about the
average, is a relationship to
the average kinetic energy.
Whereas heat is all
about the flow of energy.
So if you think of, um, if you put
like a pot on the stove, you turn
on the fire and then the fire's
heat goes into the pan, right?
That's a flow.
So that's heat.
It's all about energy.
And we'll talk about that
in later, later lectures.
Temperature is this hot, cold, right?
So just a raw value.
Let's take a look at the
different units that you will see.
So going off of Kelvin,
Celsius, Fahrenheit, let's
see how we can calculate them.
So the first unit is looking at the SI
unit of temperature, which is Kelvin.
And, but this is something that is used
in the scientific community, but most
of the world, it likes to use Celsius.
Um, which like I said is an
SI derived unit because we
can solve it using a formula.
So let's, how would we do that?
Well, in order for us to go between Kelvin
and Celsius, it's really straightforward.
Kelvin is equal to Celsius plus 273.
15.
Or if you wanted to solve
for Celsius, it's Kelvin.
minus 273.
15.
We're just adding and subtracting.
Now, keep in mind, there are some little
differences between the notation here.
If you notice next to Celsius,
there's a little, little
circle next to each of them.
This is a degree symbol.
Kelvin does not have a degree symbol
being that it is that absolute scale.
Um, it is how we measure things without
having to worry about negative values.
So it does not have that degree value.
So, let's try to practice a problem
to solve for Celsius and, or Kelvin.
Let's take a look.
Helium, which exists as a gas at room
temperatures, can become a liquid.
So think about all the helium
that you have in balloons at
birthday parties and floats.
It can become a liquid.
But that happens at 4 Kelvin.
At what temperature is that in Celsius?
So, what were we given in this problem?
So the first thing that we're
going to do is we want to kind of
highlight and underline or write down
all of the givens in the problem.
So we have 4 Kelvin.
which is given, and we want
to convert that to Celsius.
So what can we do to do that?
We are going to use Kelvin minus 273.
15, which was equal to Celsius.
We're going to use our
formula from earlier.
So let's write that down.
So Kelvin minus 273.
15.
So, let's see what our answer is.
So, our Kelvin value
is 4 Kelvin minus 273.
15.
And what we are going to get as
a final answer is negative 269.
15, uh, degrees C.
Uh, being that we only have one sig fig
though in this problem, it's kind of,
uh, really bad to me in terms of the sig
figs, but usually, uh, when we're going
through this, we are just subtracting,
so keep that in mind, we have to just
either remove or take away decimals, so we
would round this to 260 degrees C, being
that 4 Kelvin did not have any sig figs.
That would be our answer.
So we always want to put
it in the correct notation.
Okay, so that's very very cold.
Keep in mind zero degrees is freezing.
So this is negative 269 degrees C.
It's almost absolute zero.
You, your human body would
instantly freeze if you were
to come in contact with this.
and would not last very long.
Let's take a look at the next set of
units, which is Fahrenheit to Celsius.
In the USA, we use Fahrenheit, um, in
our country, uh, which, unlike the rest
of the world, which uses Celsius, we
are pretty stubborn and stuck to it.
So we have to be willing to know how to
convert to Celsius in order to speak to
the rest of the international community.
Um, it's a pretty straightforward
formula to do that.
Uh, both of them are usually
always given as references on
exams and quizzes in most courses.
Uh, but sometimes you might
need to memorize them depending
on who your teacher is and who
you are taking a course with.
Uh, but generally it's
always available to you.
You can look up the formula
at any point in time.
I know my courses, it's
always given to you.
Um, so let's say if we have Fahrenheit,
so the way that we would use this formula
is we would take the Celsius value
times it by a fraction of nine fifths.
Solve for that and then add
32 or we could take Fahrenheit
minus 32 times five ninths.
Notice how the fraction flipped
between the two and that
would give us our Celsius.
Now if you don't like fractions,
let's say a fractions are a little too
scary and a little too spooky for you.
Right?
Fractions can be a little scary.
There's an alternative version
of this, which is actually a
lot easier to kind of see here.
So the Fahrenheit is 1.
8 times Celsius.
Plus 32 or Fahrenheit
minus 32 divided by 1.
8 is equal to Celsius.
So a lot easier of a formulas to use.
You can use either one, whichever
one you prefer for your courses.
Um, usually I use, I think I usually
use this one more often on the bottom
here, but I do know some people
prefer the traditional corrections.
Let's try a practice problem to use this
compost can be made at home from grass
clippings, kitchen scraps, and dry leaves.
As microbes break down organic
matter, heat is generated.
The compost can reach temperatures
of 155 degrees Fahrenheit.
Keep in mind your body temperature was 98.
6 degrees Fahrenheit.
This is very, very hot.
Um, which kills pathogens,
meaning anything that's harmful.
What is the temperature
in Celsius and Kelvin?
Okay, so first thing you want to
do is, there's a lot of info here,
so we want to highlight and find
anything that's really important.
So we have 155 degrees Fahrenheit,
and we want to convert to Celsius.
And to Kelvin.
So, all right, first things first, 155
degrees Fahrenheit, the only formula that
we have is converting that to Celsius,
which is what we had earlier, right?
So, how, which one would
we want to use here?
Let's use the alternate version.
So, being that we want
to convert to Celsius.
We would plug in our 155
minus 32 in this format here.
So let's use it.
So if I had my Celsius right, we had 155
degrees Fahrenheit, we'll minus that by
32, and then we'll divide that by 1.8.
And what we are going to get is
68.3 degrees C as our answer,
which is very, very warm.
Now the other part of the problem.
was for us to convert this to,
um, was to convert this to Kelvin.
So how exactly would we go about
converting Celsius to Kelvin?
As we would do our 68.
3 degrees C, add to 73.
15, and this would convert us to Kelvin.
So Kelvin is going to be equal to that.
Which what we will get for
our final answer is 341.
5 Kelvin as our final answers.
Okay, so that would be both of them
here as our answers and that is how you
can solve from Celsius to Fahrenheit.
Um, or using Fahrenheit
to get Celsius and Kelvin.
Keep in mind when you're working in the
lab, we will, you will always be using
Um, Celsius, except for when you're
working generally with gas laws or, um,
different things that require the absolute
scale, but Celsius is commonplace.
Generally, in every chemical lab in the U.
S.
and the world is you have Celsius
thermometers, um, and even
more in health care facilities.
It's more common for.
Celsius to be used as
well now, even in the U.
S.
So in all professions, we are
trying to start to slowly use
Celsius more and more being that
we are an international community.
All right, this has been
all I have for temperature.
I hope this video helps you for
preparing yourself for future
labs, and I will see you all later.
Thank you so much for listening.
Bye.